<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cloud-functions on Mark Edmondson</title>
    <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/cloud-functions/</link>
    <description>Recent content in cloud-functions on Mark Edmondson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/cloud-functions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Activating GA4 events with GTM Server-Side and Pub/Sub for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/sending-ga4-events-pubsub/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/sending-ga4-events-pubsub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image from &lt;a href=&#34;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/758/brief-outburst/?category=solar-system_sun&#34;&gt;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/758/brief-outburst/?category=solar-system_sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Google Tag Manager Server-side (GTM-SS), the scope on what you can do with your GA4 events is much enhanced, since using GTM-SS you have the ability to interact easily with other GCP services, in particular easier Google authentication.  This integration can allow you to enrich your data streams or send your GA4 data to different locations other than the Google Marketing Platform.  The first example of this has been using the BigQuery API in your GTM-SS templates to export your event data, but what if you need your event data on a more real-time basis?  For that, there is &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/pubsub/docs/overview&#34;&gt;Google Pub/Sub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online payments for data science apps (DSaaS) using R, Shiny, Firebase, Paddle and Google Cloud Functions</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/datascience-aas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/datascience-aas/</guid>
      <description>This post has been delayed due to the events of 2020 including a global pandemic and social justice demonstrations, if you are touched by those I wish you all the best. For my family and I we have been very lucky and spent most of the last months tending our garden in the Copenhagen suburbs, but others have been a lot more directly affected.
One consequence of the pandemic may be that from now on more interaction will be online, which presents both opportunities and challenges.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Auto Google Analytics Data Imports from Cloud Storage</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/automatic-google-analytics-data-imports-cloud-storage/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/automatic-google-analytics-data-imports-cloud-storage/</guid>
      <description>Continuing my infatuation with cloud functions (see last post on using cloud functions to manipulate BigQuery exports) this is a post showing how to bring together various code examples out there so that you can easily upload custom data imports from a Google cloud storage bucket.
The code is available in this GitHub repo for useful cloud functions with Google Analytics
Extended data imports Google Analytics offers various versions of uploads.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
