<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>google-compute-engine on Mark Edmondson</title>
    <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/google-compute-engine/</link>
    <description>Recent content in google-compute-engine on Mark Edmondson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/google-compute-engine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>R at scale on the Google Cloud Platform</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/r-at-scale-on-google-cloud-platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/r-at-scale-on-google-cloud-platform/</guid>
      <description>This post covers my current thinking on what I consider the optimal way to work with R on the Google Cloud Platform (GCP). It seems this has developed into my niche, and I get questions about it so would like to be able to point to a URL.
Both R and the GCP rapidly evolve, so this will have to be updated I guess at some point in the future, but even as things stand now you can do some wonderful things with R, and can multiply those out to potentially billions of users with GCP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run RStudio Server on a Chromebook as a Cloud Native</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/rstudio-server-chromebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 13:55:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/rstudio-server-chromebook/</guid>
      <description>I recently got an Asus Chromebook Flip with which I&amp;rsquo;m very happy, but it did make me realise that if a Chromebook was to replace my normal desktop as my primary workstation, my RStudio Server setup would need to be more cloud native than was available up until now.
TL;DR - A how-to on making RStudio Server run on a Chromebook that automatically backs up data and configuration settings to Google Cloud Storage is on the googleComputeEngineR website here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Ways to Schedule R scripts on Google Cloud Platform</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/4-ways-schedule-r-scripts-on-google-cloud-platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/4-ways-schedule-r-scripts-on-google-cloud-platform/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;A common question I come across is how to automate scheduling of R scripts downloading data. This post goes through some options that I have played around with, which I’ve mostly used for downloading API data such as Google Analytics using the Google Cloud platform, but the same principles could apply for AWS or Azure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My R Packages</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/r-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 21:20:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/r-packages/</guid>
      <description>A full list of R packages I have published are on my Github, but some notable ones are below.
Some are part of the cloudyR project, which has many packages useful for using R in the cloud. I concentrate on the Google cloud below, but be sure to check out the other packages if you’re looking to work with AWS or other cloud based services.
CRAN     Status URL Description     googleAuthR The central workhorse for authentication on Google APIs   googleAnalyticsR Works with Google Analytics Reporting V3/V4 and Management APIs   googleComputeEngineR Launch Virtual Machines within the Google Cloud, via templates or your own Docker containers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launch RStudio Server in the Google Cloud with two lines of R</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/launch-rstudio-server-google-cloud-in-two-lines-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/launch-rstudio-server-google-cloud-in-two-lines-r/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve written previously about how to get RStudio Server running on Google Compute Engine: the first in July 2014 gave you a snapshot to download then customise, the second in April 2016 launched via a Docker container.
Things move on, and I now recommend using the process below that uses the RStudio template in the new on CRAN googleComputeEngineR package. Not only does it abstract away a lot of the dev-ops set up, but it also gives you more flexibility by taking advantage of Dockerfiles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A digital analytics workflow through the Google Cloud using R</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/digital-analytics-workflow-through-google-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/digital-analytics-workflow-through-google-cloud/</guid>
      <description>There are now several packages built upon the googleAuthR framework which are helpful to a digital analyst who uses R, so this post looks to demonstrate how they all work together. If you&amp;rsquo;re new to R, and would like to know how it helps with your digital analytics, Tim Wilson and I ran a workshop last month aimed at getting a digital analyst up and running. The course material is online at www.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scheduling R scripts for a team using RStudio Server, Docker, Github and Google Compute Engine</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/setting-up-scheduled-R-scripts-for-an-analytics-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2016 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/setting-up-scheduled-R-scripts-for-an-analytics-team/</guid>
      <description>edit 20th November, 2016 - now everything in this post is abstracted away and available in the googleComputeEngineR package - I would say its a lot easier to use that. Here is a post on getting started with it. http://code.markedmondson.me/launch-rstudio-server-google-cloud-in-two-lines-r/
This blog will give you steps that allows you to run on Google Compute Engine a server that has these features:
 RStudio Server instance with multiple login. Apache to host a welcome webpage.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>