<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>docker on Mark Edmondson</title>
    <link>/tags/docker/</link>
    <description>Recent content in docker on Mark Edmondson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/docker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>R at scale on the Google Cloud Platform</title>
      <link>/r-at-scale-on-google-cloud-platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/r-at-scale-on-google-cloud-platform/</guid>
      <description>This post covers my current thinking on what I consider the optimal way to work with R on the Google Cloud Platform (GCP). It seems this has developed into my niche, and I get questions about it so would like to be able to point to a URL.
Both R and the GCP rapidly evolve, so this will have to be updated I guess at some point in the future, but even as things stand now you can do some wonderful things with R, and can multiply those out to potentially billions of users with GCP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R on Kubernetes - serverless Shiny, R APIs and scheduled scripts</title>
      <link>/r-on-kubernetes-serverless-shiny-r-apis-and-scheduled-scripts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/r-on-kubernetes-serverless-shiny-r-apis-and-scheduled-scripts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-run-r-on-kubernetes&#34;&gt;Why run R on Kubernetes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kubernetes.io/&#34;&gt;Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt; is a free and open-source utility to run jobs within a computer cluster.  It abstracts away the servers the jobs are running on so you need only worry about the code to run.  It has features such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://kubernetes.io/docs/concepts/workloads/controllers/cron-jobs/&#34;&gt;scheduling&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/kubernetes-engine/docs/concepts/cluster-autoscaler&#34;&gt;auto-scaling&lt;/a&gt;, and auto-healing to replace nodes if they breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only need to run R on a single machine, then its probably a bit OTT to use Kubernetes, but if you are starting to work with multiple Docker containers and/or VMs it gets more and more attractive to have a way to easily orchestrate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubernetes works via &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; containers, so if you are already familiar with using Docker for abstracting away code environments, it should be a short step up to abstracting away the computers those Docker containers run upon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run RStudio Server on a Chromebook as a Cloud Native</title>
      <link>/rstudio-server-chromebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 13:55:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/rstudio-server-chromebook/</guid>
      <description>I recently got an Asus Chromebook Flip with which I&amp;rsquo;m very happy, but it did make me realise that if a Chromebook was to replace my normal desktop as my primary workstation, my RStudio Server setup would need to be more cloud native than was available up until now.
TL;DR - A how-to on making RStudio Server run on a Chromebook that automatically backs up data and configuration settings to Google Cloud Storage is on the googleComputeEngineR website here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Ways to Schedule R scripts on Google Cloud Platform</title>
      <link>/4-ways-schedule-r-scripts-on-google-cloud-platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/4-ways-schedule-r-scripts-on-google-cloud-platform/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;A common question I come across is how to automate scheduling of R scripts downloading data. This post goes through some options that I have played around with, which I’ve mostly used for downloading API data such as Google Analytics using the Google Cloud platform, but the same principles could apply for AWS or Azure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A digital analytics workflow through the Google Cloud using R</title>
      <link>/digital-analytics-workflow-through-google-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/digital-analytics-workflow-through-google-cloud/</guid>
      <description>There are now several packages built upon the googleAuthR framework which are helpful to a digital analyst who uses R, so this post looks to demonstrate how they all work together. If you&amp;rsquo;re new to R, and would like to know how it helps with your digital analytics, Tim Wilson and I ran a workshop last month aimed at getting a digital analyst up and running. The course material is online at www.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scheduling R scripts for a team using RStudio Server, Docker, Github and Google Compute Engine</title>
      <link>/setting-up-scheduled-R-scripts-for-an-analytics-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2016 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/setting-up-scheduled-R-scripts-for-an-analytics-team/</guid>
      <description>edit 20th November, 2016 - now everything in this post is abstracted away and available in the googleComputeEngineR package - I would say its a lot easier to use that. Here is a post on getting started with it. http://code.markedmondson.me/launch-rstudio-server-google-cloud-in-two-lines-r/
This blog will give you steps that allows you to run on Google Compute Engine a server that has these features:
 RStudio Server instance with multiple login. Apache to host a welcome webpage.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>