<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cloud-run on Mark Edmondson</title>
    <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/cloud-run/</link>
    <description>Recent content in cloud-run on Mark Edmondson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/cloud-run/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Google Tag Manager Server Side on Cloud Run - Pros and Cons</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/gtm-serverside-cloudrun/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/gtm-serverside-cloudrun/</guid>
      <description>One of the most exciting developments in 2020 for me is the launch of Google Tag Manager Server Side, which lies at the intersection of cloud and digital analytics that I&amp;rsquo;ve gravitated towards in recent years.
There are many good resources out there on GTM Serverside, Simo in particular has got me up to speed with his excellent range of posts. This post will assume you&amp;rsquo;ve read those, and be more about the viability of deploying GTM server side within Cloud Run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shiny on Google Cloud Run - Scale-to-Zero R Web Apps</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/shiny-cloudrun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/shiny-cloudrun/</guid>
      <description>There are some references on how to deploy Shiny apps to Cloud Run around the web and in various bits of my package documentation, but its a cool service so I thought it worth pulling out and having a blog post to refer to.
Why Shiny on Cloud Run? As mentioned in my R at scale on Google Cloud Platform post, Cloud Run is a container-as-a-service which lets you deploy Docker containers to the web without needing to worry about the infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R at scale on the Google Cloud Platform</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/r-at-scale-on-google-cloud-platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/r-at-scale-on-google-cloud-platform/</guid>
      <description>This post covers my current thinking on what I consider the optimal way to work with R on the Google Cloud Platform (GCP). It seems this has developed into my niche, and I get questions about it so would like to be able to point to a URL.
Both R and the GCP rapidly evolve, so this will have to be updated I guess at some point in the future, but even as things stand now you can do some wonderful things with R, and can multiply those out to potentially billions of users with GCP.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
