<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>google-tag-manager on Mark Edmondson</title>
    <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/google-tag-manager/</link>
    <description>Recent content in google-tag-manager on Mark Edmondson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/google-tag-manager/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Activating GA4 events with GTM Server-Side and Pub/Sub for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/sending-ga4-events-pubsub/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/sending-ga4-events-pubsub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image from &lt;a href=&#34;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/758/brief-outburst/?category=solar-system_sun&#34;&gt;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/758/brief-outburst/?category=solar-system_sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Google Tag Manager Server-side (GTM-SS), the scope on what you can do with your GA4 events is much enhanced, since using GTM-SS you have the ability to interact easily with other GCP services, in particular easier Google authentication.  This integration can allow you to enrich your data streams or send your GA4 data to different locations other than the Google Marketing Platform.  The first example of this has been using the BigQuery API in your GTM-SS templates to export your event data, but what if you need your event data on a more real-time basis?  For that, there is &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/pubsub/docs/overview&#34;&gt;Google Pub/Sub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating your own cookieless analytics tool with GTM Server Side, Cloud Run, BigQuery and Shiny</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/edmondlytica/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 09:29:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/edmondlytica/</guid>
      <description>This is an example of how GTM server side can be used to create your own digital analytics tool. It is a proof of concept of what you can do given the power of GTM server side and its BigQuery integration. I customise the stream by adding cookieless tracking, displaying the data in Shiny and running it all on Cloud Run to keep costs down but performance good.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Privacy Engineering with Google Tag Manager Server Side and Consent Mode</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/data-privacy-gtm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 09:29:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/data-privacy-gtm/</guid>
      <description>A new interest at the moment is engineering through various data privacy requirements with some of the new tools Google has available. With respect to my guiding principle of blogging about what I wish I could have read 6 months ago, I thought it worth writing about what is now possible. Data privacy engineering also requires clear thinking about the legal and technical details and so this will also help organise my communication around the subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Google Tag Manager Server Side to Trigger Webhook Events</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/gtm-serverside-webhooks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 12:50:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/gtm-serverside-webhooks/</guid>
      <description>When GTM Server Side was announced the use cases for it were not so compelling for me at first.
Sure, extra security and potential speed ups were nice to have, but it wasn’t really necessary for a lot of websites, given the cost. However, now we have had a chance to play with it and can see its integration with the rest of the Google Cloud Platform, new use cases are coming up which are very compelling, especially if the GTM Server Side costs can be driven down via Cloud Run deployments - see last post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Tag Manager Server Side on Cloud Run - Pros and Cons</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/gtm-serverside-cloudrun/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/gtm-serverside-cloudrun/</guid>
      <description>One of the most exciting developments in 2020 for me is the launch of Google Tag Manager Server Side, which lies at the intersection of cloud and digital analytics that I&amp;rsquo;ve gravitated towards in recent years.
There are many good resources out there on GTM Serverside, Simo in particular has got me up to speed with his excellent range of posts. This post will assume you&amp;rsquo;ve read those, and be more about the viability of deploying GTM server side within Cloud Run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My R Packages</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/r-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 21:20:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/r-packages/</guid>
      <description>A full list of R packages I have published are on my Github, but some notable ones are below.
Some are part of the cloudyR project, which has many packages useful for using R in the cloud. I concentrate on the Google cloud below, but be sure to check out the other packages if you’re looking to work with AWS or other cloud based services.
CRAN     Status URL Description     googleAuthR The central workhorse for authentication on Google APIs   googleAnalyticsR Works with Google Analytics Reporting V3/V4 and Management APIs   googleComputeEngineR Launch Virtual Machines within the Google Cloud, via templates or your own Docker containers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time forecasting dashboard with Google Tag Manager, Google Cloud and R Shiny - Part two</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 14:20:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-2/</guid>
      <description>In part two of this two part series we walk through the steps to stream data from a Google Tag Manager (GTM) implementation into a Google App Engine (GAE) web app, which then adds data to a BigQuery table via BigQuery&amp;rsquo;s data streaming capability. In part two, we go into how to query that table in realtime from R, make a forecast using R, then visualise it in Shiny and the JavaScript visualisation library Highcharts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time forecasting dashboard with Google Tag Manager, Google Cloud and R Shiny - Part one</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-1/</guid>
      <description>In part one of this two part series we walk through the steps to stream data from a Google Tag Manager (GTM) implementation into a Google App Engine (GAE) web app, which then adds data to a BigQuery table via BigQuery&amp;rsquo;s data streaming capability. In part two, we go into how to query that table in realtime from R, make a forecast using R, then visualise it in Shiny and the JavaScript visualisation library Highcharts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
