<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>google-tag-manager on Mark Edmondson</title>
    <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/google-tag-manager/</link>
    <description>Recent content in google-tag-manager on Mark Edmondson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/google-tag-manager/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Activating GA4 events with GTM Server-Side and Pub/Sub for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/sending-ga4-events-pubsub/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/sending-ga4-events-pubsub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image from &lt;a href=&#34;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/758/brief-outburst/?category=solar-system_sun&#34;&gt;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/758/brief-outburst/?category=solar-system_sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Google Tag Manager Server-side (GTM-SS), the scope on what you can do with your GA4 events is much enhanced, since using GTM-SS you have the ability to interact easily with other GCP services, in particular easier Google authentication.  This integration can allow you to enrich your data streams or send your GA4 data to different locations other than the Google Marketing Platform.  The first example of this has been using the BigQuery API in your GTM-SS templates to export your event data, but what if you need your event data on a more real-time basis?  For that, there is &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/pubsub/docs/overview&#34;&gt;Google Pub/Sub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Tag Manager Server Side on Cloud Run - Pros and Cons</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/gtm-serverside-cloudrun/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/gtm-serverside-cloudrun/</guid>
      <description>One of the most exciting developments in 2020 for me is the launch of Google Tag Manager Server Side, which lies at the intersection of cloud and digital analytics that I&amp;rsquo;ve gravitated towards in recent years.
There are many good resources out there on GTM Serverside, Simo in particular has got me up to speed with his excellent range of posts. This post will assume you&amp;rsquo;ve read those, and be more about the viability of deploying GTM server side within Cloud Run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time forecasting dashboard with Google Tag Manager, Google Cloud and R Shiny - Part two</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 14:20:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-2/</guid>
      <description>In part two of this two part series we walk through the steps to stream data from a Google Tag Manager (GTM) implementation into a Google App Engine (GAE) web app, which then adds data to a BigQuery table via BigQuery&amp;rsquo;s data streaming capability. In part two, we go into how to query that table in realtime from R, make a forecast using R, then visualise it in Shiny and the JavaScript visualisation library Highcharts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time forecasting dashboard with Google Tag Manager, Google Cloud and R Shiny - Part one</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-1/</guid>
      <description>In part one of this two part series we walk through the steps to stream data from a Google Tag Manager (GTM) implementation into a Google App Engine (GAE) web app, which then adds data to a BigQuery table via BigQuery&amp;rsquo;s data streaming capability. In part two, we go into how to query that table in realtime from R, make a forecast using R, then visualise it in Shiny and the JavaScript visualisation library Highcharts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
