<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>python on Mark Edmondson</title>
    <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in python on Mark Edmondson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Running Large Language Models on Google Cloud Platform via Cloud Run, VertexAI and PubSub - LLMOps on GCP</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/running-llms-on-gcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/running-llms-on-gcp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello blog, its been a long time.  Since I finished the GA4 book I have had a good break and lots of life events have happened such as a new job, philosophies and family arrangements, but I have always intended to pick this thread up again once I had an idea on where it would best lead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As old readers may remember, I&amp;rsquo;ve always tried to work on the meta-horizons of where I am, restlessly looking for the next exciting lesson, and that impulse has led me to Large Language Models (LLMs) sparked off by the Chat-GPT revolution, but foreshadowed by the image generation models such as Stable Diffusion a few months before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key facilitator has been Harrison Chase&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://python.langchain.com&#34;&gt;Langchain&lt;/a&gt;, an active hive of open-source goodness.  It has allowed me to learn and imagine and digest this new active field of LLMops (Large Language Model Operations), that is the data engineering to make LLMs actually useful on a day to day basis.  I took it upon myself to see how I could apply my Google Cloud Platform (GCP) data engineering background to these new toys Langchain has helped provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means I now have this new brain, Edmonbrain, that I converse with daily in Google Chat, Slack and Discord.  I have fed it in interesting URLs, Git repos and Whitepapers so I can build up a unique bot of my very own.  I fed it my own book, and can ask it questions about it, for example:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Activating GA4 events with GTM Server-Side and Pub/Sub for Fun and Profit</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/sending-ga4-events-pubsub/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/sending-ga4-events-pubsub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image from &lt;a href=&#34;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/758/brief-outburst/?category=solar-system_sun&#34;&gt;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/758/brief-outburst/?category=solar-system_sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Google Tag Manager Server-side (GTM-SS), the scope on what you can do with your GA4 events is much enhanced, since using GTM-SS you have the ability to interact easily with other GCP services, in particular easier Google authentication.  This integration can allow you to enrich your data streams or send your GA4 data to different locations other than the Google Marketing Platform.  The first example of this has been using the BigQuery API in your GTM-SS templates to export your event data, but what if you need your event data on a more real-time basis?  For that, there is &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/pubsub/docs/overview&#34;&gt;Google Pub/Sub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online payments for data science apps (DSaaS) using R, Shiny, Firebase, Paddle and Google Cloud Functions</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/datascience-aas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/datascience-aas/</guid>
      <description>This post has been delayed due to the events of 2020 including a global pandemic and social justice demonstrations, if you are touched by those I wish you all the best. For my family and I we have been very lucky and spent most of the last months tending our garden in the Copenhagen suburbs, but others have been a lot more directly affected.
One consequence of the pandemic may be that from now on more interaction will be online, which presents both opportunities and challenges.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Auto Google Analytics Data Imports from Cloud Storage</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/automatic-google-analytics-data-imports-cloud-storage/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/automatic-google-analytics-data-imports-cloud-storage/</guid>
      <description>Continuing my infatuation with cloud functions (see last post on using cloud functions to manipulate BigQuery exports) this is a post showing how to bring together various code examples out there so that you can easily upload custom data imports from a Google cloud storage bucket.
The code is available in this GitHub repo for useful cloud functions with Google Analytics
Extended data imports Google Analytics offers various versions of uploads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time forecasting dashboard with Google Tag Manager, Google Cloud and R Shiny - Part two</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 14:20:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-2/</guid>
      <description>In part two of this two part series we walk through the steps to stream data from a Google Tag Manager (GTM) implementation into a Google App Engine (GAE) web app, which then adds data to a BigQuery table via BigQuery&amp;rsquo;s data streaming capability. In part two, we go into how to query that table in realtime from R, make a forecast using R, then visualise it in Shiny and the JavaScript visualisation library Highcharts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time forecasting dashboard with Google Tag Manager, Google Cloud and R Shiny - Part one</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/real-time-GTM-google-cloud-r-shiny-1/</guid>
      <description>In part one of this two part series we walk through the steps to stream data from a Google Tag Manager (GTM) implementation into a Google App Engine (GAE) web app, which then adds data to a BigQuery table via BigQuery&amp;rsquo;s data streaming capability. In part two, we go into how to query that table in realtime from R, make a forecast using R, then visualise it in Shiny and the JavaScript visualisation library Highcharts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
