<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blogging on Mark Edmondson</title>
    <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/blogging/</link>
    <description>Recent content in blogging on Mark Edmondson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 11:04:50 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://code.markedmondson.me/tags/blogging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why and How I&#39;m writing a GA4 book called &#39;Learning Google Analytics&#39; for O&#39;Reilly</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/writing-a-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2021 11:04:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/writing-a-book/</guid>
      <description>If you’ve been within two meters of me recently you may have heard I’m writing a book on Google Analytics 4 and I’m very excited about it. In this blog post I want to write about how it came about, and to give some love to the blog to show its not being neglected for its younger cousin, The Book.
I want to cover how the book deal came about in case you are thinking about writing one too, the process of writing itself and how my attitude to writing has changed as a result.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Blog Down</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/new-blog-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 22:45:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/new-blog-down/</guid>
      <description>A new year, a new blogging platform!
This time I’m moving from Jekyll to RStudio’s new blogdown format.
This keeps the advantages of Jekyll (a static, high performance website; markdown for editing; free hosting on Github) but with the extra bonus of being able to render in RMarkdown plus adding some nice looking capabilities from the Hugo project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jekyll &#43; Github &#43; Markdown = Blog</title>
      <link>https://code.markedmondson.me/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 23:03:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://code.markedmondson.me/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Hello World! Welcome to my new home for code blogging. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep the regular blog for all the other stuff, running on Posthaven.
Why? Its educational, and free, and writing code posts using Posthaven&amp;rsquo;s rich text editor was sometimes painful.
Using this setup means its all written in Markdown so I get control over everything just the way I want it, and since it combines Github and Markdown, two things I know well already, Jekyll seemed worth knowing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>